Hello everyone and welcome to the content
video going over section
2.9 of your textbook.
It says intro to data science, basic
descriptive statistics, but really
we're going to talk about min,
max, and range in this video. So
rather than going through the
textbook and reading through all these
examples, I'm just going to jump over
into my code space and we're just
going to do a couple of examples
together. So min, max, and range.
So very first, and the reason
we're just jumping into examples is
because these are fairly straightforward
concepts. So there's just
there are three functions that
we'll use. The first one is min.
Let's make a variable.
We'll call it minimum.
That's probably not
spelled right. So if I
know that's a function.
Let's call it min.
That's my variable name. Whoops.
And I am going to set it equal to
or assign it the value of the result
of the function call of the minimum
function. And what the minimum
function needs is it needs some
kind of a comma separated list of
values. So I'm going to give it one.
I'm going to say one, two, three,
four, five, and let's just call it
good for there. If I run this, we
would expect to see the output. Oh,
I should probably print the output.
If I run this, we would
expect the minimum function
to return to us one. But
what if I was to throw on
maybe, I don't know, negative
five at the end of there?
Then the minimum function
would return to me
the smallest value within
that set of values.
And similarly, I'm just
gonna copy all this code and
paste it down here, except
I'm gonna change it to max.
The maximum, or did I say that
right? Yeah, the maximum function
returns us the biggest value in the
set. So if I run this on the exact
same list of numbers, which is why
I copied it, then we should see
our output being 5. And that would
be true if I threw on a bigger
number here, it would give me the
biggest number in that result list.
So then we get to the range
function which kind of gives us
sets of values that we could
use min or max on so let's write
let's do an example here i'm
going to make a variable i'll call
it r and i'm going to assign it
the value of the range function
and let's do a range of 10
and then let's just print out
what that gives me you guys
can kind of see for yourself
oh hang on actually this is accurate
so it's just kind of a silly
example let me let me do something
slightly different let me say I'm going
to do a for loop which you may or
may not know at this point in the
course that's all right I'm going
to say for i in range 10 print i so
what we're doing is instead of just
printing out the entire range of
numbers which this right here in our
output that did print out the range.
0 to 10 is is the range that we
gave it and that's what it printed
out. What we're going to do is we're
going to we're going to loop through
our range. Now we're going to print
out the numbers one at a time.
So now in our output you can see
0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.
Now that is a range of 10 numbers
right because we start at 0 and
0 counts as a number, we go up to
9. So it is 10 numbers, but it goes
up to but not including the number
that we input into our range.
Notice what changes when I say 1,
10.
So I want a range of
numbers from 1 to 10.
We get 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8,
9. So still not including 10. And
in this case, how many numbers
do we actually output? It's only
9 numbers, right? So we got 1,
2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, right? So
that's only nine numbers we're
not getting a range of 10 numbers
even though we're giving it
the value of 10 to give us a
range up to so if we wanted to
include something like 10 in our
upper limit we could do a plus
one on the end of our range
function and that would give us
10 or we could just tell ourselves
computers start counting at
zero and so if I wanted to
include a number, I just need to
go one bigger than that number.
And there it is.
The range function also has
a cool thing called a step,
and so if I was to throw
in maybe negative 1 here,
actually this might break.
Yeah, it didn't really print
anything. Let's do a range of 1
to negative 10, and the step
of negative 1 is actually going
to give us a backwards range.
So instead of going forwards,
one, the default is for it to
just give us a step of one going
forwards. That's why we get a
normal looking range of numbers. But
if I gave it a step of negative
one, it would count backwards.
So here we've got zero,
negative one. Actually,
it starts at one. It
goes to negative nine.
I could also give it a
step of negative two. And
I maybe ask yourself, what
should that give us before
I run the code and maybe
see if you can guess.
So this gives us every other negative
number going up to negative 9.
And the same would be true if
we change this to positive.
So a step of 1 to 10, or
sorry, a range of 1 to 10, step
of 2 would give us positive
numbers every other number.
And we could do that step of
however many. So that's everything
for this content video.
Thanks Thanks for watching.